<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Troubleshoot on Ef&#39;s log</title>
    <link>https://fahmifj.github.io/tags/troubleshoot/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Troubleshoot on Ef&#39;s log</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 07:07:50 +0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://fahmifj.github.io/tags/troubleshoot/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Me vs Windows Permissions</title>
      <link>https://fahmifj.github.io/blog/me-vs-windows-permissions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 07:07:50 +0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://fahmifj.github.io/blog/me-vs-windows-permissions/</guid>
      <description>Facing weird error on Windows 10? Then maybe this post could help you</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I wanted to upgrade my Microsoft Office, and then planned to clean up my Windows laptop from unused programs, particularly the ones installed by chocolatey (Windows package manager). But, you guess it, things don&rsquo;t always go as planned.</p>
<p>The first problem I encounter was <code>Error Code: 30015-4 (5)</code> while trying to re-install my Microsoft Office, and then several  <code>C:\ProgramData\Microsoft\Windows GetLastError:5</code> error messages. These problems were related to Windows permissions, and I suspect that they were caused by a Microsoft troubleshooter tool called <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/100607">SaRA</a>. The tool might have accidentally messed up the Windows permissions during the process of cleaning up my previous Microsoft Office. As a result, my Windows no longer be able to install or remove some apps.</p>
<p>I was able to resolve these problems by manually resetting the permissions of the respective app folders back to their original state. So, I think it would be fun to post the walkthrough (it might be boring for you 😅).</p>
<h2 id="the-problems">The Problems</h2>
<p>The first problem I ran into was <code>Error Code: 30015-4(5)</code> during the installation of Microsoft Office.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721040950497.png" alt="image-20210721040950497"  title="Error Code: 30015-4 (5)"  /></div>
</p>
<p>I clicked on the online help, and it was pointing out to <a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/office/fix-office-installation-errors-d5df89a9-0507-4b4c-92f9-22f457e630aa?ns=ocsac2rinstall&amp;version=16&amp;syslcid=1033&amp;uilcid=1033&amp;appver=cin160&amp;helpid=%225-4-30015%22&amp;ui=en-us&amp;rs=en-us&amp;ad=us">this page</a>. At the bottom of the page, it offers an &ldquo;easy fix&rdquo; tool to resolve the problem above. I downloaded and ran that tool, but the error remains 🙃.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721041358098.png" alt="image-20210721041358098"  title="An easy fix tool that resulted in another chaos"  /></div>
</p>
<p>At this point, I couldn&rsquo;t install or uninstall any applications wrapped with Windows Installer (<code>.msi</code>) anymore, including NodeJS. It&rsquo;s the same problem as the one in my <a href="https://fahmifj.github.io/blog/play-with-printnightmare/">PrintNightmare</a> post, in which my Visual Studio refuses to install the Windows SDK.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="./imgs/image-20210718024015408.png" alt="image-20210718024015408"  /></div>
</p>
<p>And somehow, this also affects my laptop&rsquo;s WiFi functionality/features, such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Unable to save WiFi profiles, auto-connect no longer works.</li>
<li>Unable to turn on the mobile hotspot feature</li>
<li>The &ldquo;Forget&rdquo; and &ldquo;Properties&rdquo; options are missing when a right-click is performed on a WiFi connection.</li>
</ul>
<p>The most weird one is a stack-based buffer error came from my WiFi settings.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721050915867.png" alt="image-20210721050915867"  title="Stack-based buffer error"  /></div>
</p>
<p>The stack-based buffer error raises when I clicked any currently in use Wi-Fi connection from the Wi-Fi settings.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721053820002.png" alt="image-20210721053820002"  title="WiFi Settings"  /></div>
</p>
<p>Also, the &ldquo;Forget&rdquo; and &ldquo;Properties&rdquo; options were missing. I found a similar issue <a href="https://answers.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/forum/all/windows-10-doesnt-save-wifi-network-resolved/16ae1129-e24b-4268-91c4-acc4446966fa">here</a> but the solution doesn&rsquo;t suite my environment.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721054401662.png" alt="image-20210721054401662"  title="Missing the Forget and the Properties options"  /></div>
</p>
<h2 id="finding-the-root-cause">Finding The Root Cause</h2>
<p>Searching for <code>Error Code: 30015-4  (5)</code> on the Microsoft Support site didn&rsquo;t really help, so I started to search for the official documentation about error code, and I found <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/debug/system-error-codes--0-499-">this page</a>. I couldn&rsquo;t find anything about &ldquo;30015-4&rdquo; in that page, but I think I did know what &ldquo;(5)&rdquo; meant.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721043547662.png" alt="image-20210721043547662"  /></div>
</p>
<p>At this point, it was clear that these problems were related to the system permissions (even my Wi-Fi problem).</p>
<p>I started to investigate <code>C:\Program Files\</code> and <code>C:\Program Files (x86)\</code> (the default folder for installed apps), but no problems were found there.  So the next one is <code>C:\ProgramData</code>, where all application data is stored/created.</p>
<p>While investigating all the folders under <code>C:\ProgramData\</code> and <code>C:\ProgramData\Microsoft</code>, I noticed that some of the folders only have my account listed in their security properties.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721044802348.png" alt="image-20210721044802348"  title="Bad Permissions on Office folder"  /></div>
</p>
<p>Normally, the folder permissions under <code>C:\ProgramData</code> should be configured similar to the image below (taken from VirtualBox folder) .</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721045334784.png" alt="image-20210721045334784"  title="Good Permissions: Basic"  /></div>
</p>
<p>And here are the advanced permission settings.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721045624596.png" alt="image-20210721045624596"  title="Good Permissions: Advanced Settings"  /></div>
</p>
<p>Now I know how the default permissions look like, and I can use this as a template to fix the other folders with bad permissions.</p>
<h2 id="fix-the-problems">Fix The Problems</h2>
<h3 id="office-error-code-30015-4-5">Office Error Code: 30015-4 (5)</h3>
<p>This error <code>Error Code: 30015-4 (5)</code> can be resolved by enabling the inheritance on the respective app folder, which is <code>C:\ProgramData\Microsoft\OFFICE</code>. So that the permissions of the  <code>Microsoft</code> folder will be inherited to the <code>OFFICE</code> folder. I will also remove my account, &ldquo;Fahmi FJ&rdquo;, from the permission entries.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721051824838.png" alt="image-20210721051824838"  title="Fix Office Error Code: 30015-4(5)"  /></div>
</p>
<p>If you&rsquo;re not sure about this, do check the other folders&rsquo; permissions under the same parent folder. Using this case, then the parent folder is <code>C:\ProgramData\Microsoft\</code>,  and the child are any folders under <code>C:\ProgramData\Microsoft\[child]</code>.</p>
<p>I got my Ms Office back now.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721053920106.png" alt="image-20210721053920106"  /></div>
</p>
<h3 id="getlasterror5">GetLastError:5</h3>
<p>Any <code>GetLastError:5</code>, can be resolved using the same method as above, by enabling the inheritance to the affected application folder.</p>
<p>In my case, I got the following error message from chocolatey and node.js:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-shell" data-lang="shell"><span class="line"><span class="cl">C:<span class="se">\P</span>rogramData<span class="se">\M</span>icrosoft<span class="se">\W</span>indows<span class="se">\S</span>tart Menu<span class="se">\P</span>rograms GetLastError: <span class="m">5</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Then, first, I should look into the permissions of <code>Microsoft</code> folder, then <code>Windows</code> folder, and then <code>Start Menu</code> folder, and it turned out the problem is in the <code>Windows</code> folder permissions. So, to resolve this problem, I have to inherit the <code>Microsoft</code> folder permissions to the <code>Windows</code> folder, see image below.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721114505028.png" alt="image-20210721114505028"  /></div>
</p>
<p>And then, I will revert the <code>Start Menu</code> folder permissions to default, see image below.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721114911619.png" alt="image-20210721114911619"  /></div>
</p>
<p>Finally inherit the <code>Start Menu</code> folder permissions to the <code>Programs</code> folder.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721115022365.png" alt="image-20210721115022365"  /></div>
</p>
<p>Again, if you&rsquo;re not sure about this, and didn&rsquo;t want to reinstall your Windows, try install a fresh Windows on Virtual Machine / Cloud and inspect the default permission settings.</p>
<h3 id="stack-based-and-wifi-error">Stack-based and WiFi error</h3>
<p>This section may resolve the following problems.</p>
<ul>
<li>SystemSettings.exe - System Error: The system detected an overrun of a blabla..</li>
<li>Windows won&rsquo;t remember Wi-Fi password</li>
<li>The &ldquo;Forget&rdquo; and &ldquo;Properties&rdquo; options are missing from Wi-Fi connection.</li>
<li>Mobile Hotspot Wi-Fi</li>
</ul>
<p>In my case the root cause of these problems was also the folder permission.</p>
<p>In Windows, all Wi-Fi profiles are stored in <code>C:\ProgramData\Microsoft\Wlansvc\Profiles</code>, so if the permissions are messed up, the system is most likely to crash or partially working. In my case, my laptop is able to connect to any Wi-Fi network, but it can&rsquo;t remember the Wi-Fi profile, so I have to re-enter my Wi-Fi password every time I want to connect. This caused by the system didn&rsquo;t have write access on <code>C:\ProgramData\Microsoft\Wlansvc\Profiles</code>.</p>
<p>But, after reverting the permissions of  the <code>Wlansvc</code> folder , the WiFi functionality/features returned back to normal.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721055011183.png" alt="image-20210721055011183"  /></div>
</p>
<p>It also fixed the missing options and auto-connect.</p>
<p><div class="img-container"><img src="imgs/image-20210721055107535.png" alt="image-20210721055107535"  /></div>
</p>
<p>Also, there is no more error about &ldquo;<em>The system detected an overrun of a stack-based buffer in this  application. This overrun could potentially allow a malicious user to  gain control of this application</em>&rdquo; on the Wi-Fi settings.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Padahal cuma mau reinstall Office, merembetnya kemana-mana 🙃.</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>That&rsquo;s all! I hope this post helps you too.</p>
<p>I will try to keep this post updated whenever I face the same problem related to Windows Permissions.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
